let's move now to the last part we are going to
discuss thrashing this is actually one of the
parts that is usually a bit more complicated
so there is this thing called thrashing is
something that can happen during your
execution and it's based on the following if
a process does not have enough pages because
there are not enough frames that the process can
use then you will have a high number of page faults
now you know that when you have a page fault
there is this routine to fetch the page that maybe
you have to swap out so when there is a page fault
you start using the disk and that of course has an
implication because you have a lot of input/output
what happens is that since the process
now is spending more time waiting for/reading
and writing to the disk than actually running
it starts behaving like an IO-bound process
rather than a CPU-bound process and its
CPU consumption goes down now if your operating
system is naive and it just assumes that since the
process it's not using a lot of CPU then it means
that I have free CPU I can use for other processes
what happens is that the scheduler will run more
processes but these processes will also generate a
lot of page faults because they will be also
fighting to get frames that are not really
available so this degenerates because the
more you see that the CPU is not being used
the more you add processes and the less the CPU
will be used because also these processes will be
fighting for the same frames or the same physical
memory that is not enough and this is what
thrashing is when a process needs frames and
here we are of course in global page replacement
it steals from other processes then you start
having input/output waiting because you have to
move the processes into the queues of those
waiting for the disk to read and write pages
you think that you can run more stuff because most
of the processes are waiting rather than
in the ready queue so you increase even more
but this results in those news processes you
want to run to steal frames from the
other processes and this degenerates
so this is the effect on the CPU utilization when
you increase the degree of multi-programming in
the beginning it gets better you use more CPU but
if you go above a certain threshold then the CPU
utilization collapses and this phase here this
part of the graph is where you are entering the
thrashing mode which means this might sound
strange but it basically means that sometimes
if you want to use more CPU you should
decrease the parallelism degree now
how do we know or how can we know that
paging / virtual memory is working and
we don't end up into thrashing well we have
this concept that we discussed before about
locality we said that when we run
a process we are not really using
all the pages all the time at the same time but
that during portions of time we are going to use
a subset of pages maybe the ones that are related
to a certain function and then we move to another
function so we change locality and so on
so if we want to avoid trashing what we need
to make sure is that the space we have is enough
to maintain at the same time all the localities
of the processes we are trying to run it's
not about all the space the processes need
it's about the space that is needed by their
localities so this is just an example this is
a graph in which you have the execution time
and then you have a small dot every time a certain
process is accessing some of his pages so
what this figure is trying to show you is that
you can see that during this portion of time here
pages 18 to 24 here and 30 to 34 are being used
so you see here this is empty so it means that
that is not part of the current locality because
you don't really try to access these pages but at
a certain point here the locality changes so now
for example these three pages here are
no longer used and these pages that were
not used before they start being used now so
you can see that is changing locality over time so
how can the operating system in practice avoid
entering the thrashing mode one way to go
is to use the working set model so you
define a window a working set window it's
a fixed number of page references could be
the last 10 000 instructions for example
then you keep track looking only at the last 10000
instructions at the set of pages that you are
trying to that is currently being used by the
by the process and you assume that
the size of the locality is the size of this
set so here you could have five pages and
now you could have two pages so these are two
different locations now you can imagine that one
key question here is how do you decide how big the
window should be because if you make it too small
then you will not really encompass the entire
locality so you might think that you have space
for enough to fit your locality but actually your
locality is bigger so you don't really have it
on the other end if you pick it too big then
you might encompass several localities and
so you might think the opposite I don't have
enough free space because my locality is bigger
but actually no your locality is not that big it's
just that the window you take it's too big and
what you can check is the sum of all the
localities at each point in time and if
this is more than the available frames then you
are clearly entering into the thrashing mode
so in that case you want to suspend or swap out
some of the processes or at least one of them
so again challenge here how do you keep track of
the working set how do you choose the window size?
an alternative you can use to the working set
model it's actually to look at the page fault
frequency so you can define two bounds
for the frequency with which you can
you observe sorry page faults and you
decide whether to allocate or remove frames
and on the long run whether to swap out a process
depending on how many page faults you get so
as long as they stay within the given boundaries
it is okay if they go above you can ask for more
frames and below you can release frames and
when you have many that are above then you can
suspend some of them now here you see that you
have two different alternatives and actually
they are connected so as always one of the
challenges here is that you don't really know how
to choose the window set or the specific
number of page faults you can tolerate until
you actually start running your operating system
and see what processes the user is trying to run
how many of them how many cores you have available
and so on and so forth and here you can also
see that there is a direct relationship between
the working set and the page fault rate because
what you will see over time if you just
look at the page fault rate is that
usually you start observing an increasing page
fault rate when there is a new locality because
the processes start accessing pages that are
not loaded right now then at a certain point
this peak goes down because now all the pages of
that locality have been requested so they have been
swapped in and for a certain period of time the
the page faults will be low because the process
is still accessing the same set of pages that have
been loaded yet some of them might be swapped out
because of other processes stealing frames but
the number of page faults remains low then all
of a sudden it starts growing again because you
know the process is entering a different locality
and so on so actually if you want to find
an approximation of how big the working set
could be or should be to be the
correct one then you can monitor the
rate with which you observe page faults
in your operating system but as you can
see this now becomes complicated because of
this relationship between the two measures